Margaret Cooper Papers 133
People's Archive, MLK Library
Margaret Cooper Papers
1918-1998
People's Archive, MLK Library
Cooper, Margaret
133
6 Boxes
Arrangement
Series 1: Correspondence Series 2: Newspaper Clippings Series 3: Photographs Series 4: Organizations and Institutions Series 5: Certificates, Awards, and Recognition Series 6: Ephemera Series 7: Local and Federal Government Series 8: Books
Biographical / Historical
Margaret Cooper was born in Warrington, Virginia on August 8, 1900. She attended Martha Washington Vocational School in Washington, D.C. Cooper was known to the Shaw neighborhood as "Mother Cooper." She worked as a Registered Nurse at George Washington University Hospital. Cooper was active as a member of the Third Baptist Church in Washington, D.C. at 1546 5th Street NW. She worked as an activist in the Shaw neighborhood on numerous projects with various organizations such as the Shaw Project Area Committee, Junior Christian Endeavor, Boy Scouts of America, War on Rats, Federation of Civic associations, and the United Planning Organization. Cooper also served on the Advisory Neighborhood Commission (ANC) and was one of the first ANC commissioners for the Shaw neighborhood. Cooper lived on Warren Street NW from 1917 until her death on April 6, 2000 at the Hartland Health Center in Hyattsville, Maryland.
Custodial History
The collection came to the library as a donation, and was accessioned into the Library's collection in 2000.
Scope and Contents
This six box collection consists of the personal papers of Margaret Cooper and documents her professional; civic and community activities; and achievements. The collection consists largely of certificates, plaques, programs, administrative materials, and miscellaneous materials documenting Cooper's involvement as an active member and leader of several organizations and institutions, including Third Baptist Church, Christian Endeavor, D.C. Federation of Civic Associations, Inc., the East Central Civic Association, the Neighborhood Advisory Committee, the Young Men's Christian Association, the National Capital Area Boy Scouts of America, Model Cities, and the United Planning Organization. Correspondence, certificates, and letters of recommendation document her work as a staff member at George Washington University Hospital. Newspaper clippings recording her achievements reflect Ms. Cooper's legacy as a pillar in her community. The collection also includes funeral programs, cards, thank you notes, photographs, political buttons, posters, books, and ephemera.
City churches; Shaw (Washington, D.C.); Citizens' Associations; Politics and government; Education, higher; Ephemera; Political activists; Neighborhood government; Neighborhoods; Women; African Americans; Police; Black persons
- Series 1: Correspondence, 1 Boxes
  Scope and Contents
  This series includes letters of appreciation and recommendation written to Margaret Cooper, holding her in high regard as a nurse and a member of the Shaw community.
  - General, 1964-1981 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Letters of Appreciation, 1955-1994 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Letters of Recommendation, 1956-1961 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Series 2: Newspaper Clippings, 1 Boxes
  This series includes biographical articles celebrating Margaret Cooper as a pillar of the Shaw Community. Also included are clippings from the Sentry Post, The Washington Informer, and the Washington Afro American.
  - Article copies (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - General, 1972-1998 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Series 3: Photographs, 1 Boxes
  Photograph subjects in this series include Walter Washington, Margaret Cooper, and the Boy Scouts of America pack 594.
  - Margaret Cooper at Podium (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Ward 2 Commissioner Thorpe, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - National Capital Area Boy Scouts of America, Pack 594 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Autographed Portrait of Man (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Walter Washington and unidentified woman, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Model Cities (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Series 4: Organizations and Institutions, 3 Boxes
  This series includes materials from the various organizations with which Margaret Cooper was affiliated. These include the Third Baptist Church, Christian Endeavor, The East Central Civic Association, and the National Capital Area Boy Scouts of America.
  - Lott Carey Baptist Foreign Mission Center, Events and Programs, 1997-1998 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Christian Endeavor, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Christian Endeavor; Certificates, Awards, and Recognition, 1977-1993 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - The Baptist Sunday Union of Washington And Vicinity (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - The Standard Leadership Curriculum Cards, 1955-1999 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Third Baptist Church; Certificates, Awards, and Recognition, 1954-1996 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Third Baptist Church; Events and Programs, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Third Baptist Church; Events and Programs, 1993-1996 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Third Baptist Church, Events and Programs, 1918-1993 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Third Baptist Church, Constitution, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Certificates, Awards, and Recognition, 1996-1997 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Baltimore Annual Conference African Methodist Episcopal Church, Program and Directory, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - East Central Civic Association, Shawfest, 1989-1996 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Household of Ruth, 1927-1983 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Africare, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - D.C. Federation of Civic Associations, General, 1981-1987 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - D.C. Federation of Civic Associations, Events and Programs, 1985-1997 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Young Men's Christian Association (YMCA), 1973-1978 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - The George Washington University; Certificates, Awards and Recognition, 1964-1968 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Neighborhood Advisory Committee (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Environment-Concerned Institutions, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - United Planning Organization, Events and Programs, 1978-1992 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - United Planning Organization; Certificates, Awards, and Recognition, 1970-1984 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - United Planning Organization, Correspondence, 1969-1978 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - East Central Civic Association; Certificates, Awards and Recognition, 1967-1995 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - East Central Civic Association, General, 1997 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - East Central Civic Association, Correspondence, 1977-1991 (Box 2, Box 15)
  - Shaw Project Area Committee, Inc; Certificates, Awards, and Recognition, 1977-1978 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Senior Citizens Organizations, Events and Programs, 1995-1998 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Senior Citizens Organizations; Certificates, Awards, and Recognition, 1985-1987 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - People's Involvement Corporation; Certificates, Awards, and Institutions, 1970-1971 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Shaw/Coalition Redevelopment Corporation, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Neighborhood Advisory Council of Neighborhood Development Center #1, Constitution, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - National Capital Area Boy Scouts of America, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - National Capital Area Boy Scouts of America; Certificates, Awards, and Recognition, 1973-1983 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - National Capital Area Council Boy Scouts of America, Events and Programs, 1976-1982 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Dues Cards and Donation Envelope, 1992-1997 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Third Baptist Church, Membership Certificate, 1978 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Environmental Improvement Award, 1986 (Box 4, Folder 8)
- Series 5: Certificates, Awards, and Recognition, 1 Boxes
  This series includes certificates and recognition for participation and leadership. also included is information regarding the park dedicated in honor of Margaret Cooper's years of community service.
  - Community Awards and Recognition, 1971-1992 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Park Dedication, 1996 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Citizens Organized Patrol Efforts (C.O.P. E.), 1991 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Series 6: Ephemera, 3 Boxes
  This series includes stickers, buttons, programs, flyers, cards, and other materials from community organizations, institutions, and individuals.
  - Citizens Advisory Committee to Reduce Litter, Stickers (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - D.C. Statehood, Bumper Stickers and Mailing (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Song Lyrics and Poems, 1986-1996 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - The Lincoln Theatre, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Programs and Flyers, 1949 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Brochures, 1977-1995 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Copied Photograph (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - David Clarke Campaign Stickers (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Obituaries and Funeral Programs, 1992-1997 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Government Materials, 1969 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Anniversary Programs, 1986-1991 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Pick Temple, Autographed Cards (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Cards and Thank You Notes, 1964-1998 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Mid-City Tenants Action Council, Urban Renewal Area; Blank Membership Cards (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Ribbons, 1986 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Identification Badges (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - National Capital Area Boy Scouts of America, 1972-1981 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Buttons, Fauntroy (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Buttons, Marion Barry (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Buttons, Shawfest '89, 1989 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Buttons, Model City (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Buttons, War on Rats (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Buttons, D.C. Commission for Women (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Buttons, "Re-Elect Wilson Ward 2" (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Buttons, "Bringin' back The Lincoln '91", 1991 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Buttons, "Zais Ward 2" (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Buttons, "Sharon Pratt Dixon for Mayor" (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Buttons, Family Life Center Training Conference, 1988 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Buttons, Arrington Dixon (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Buttons, Minority Business Opportunity Commission, Office of Human Rights (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Buttons, D.C. Lung Association (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Buttons, Wilson Council Chairman (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Buttons, "I'm for the Bottle Bill" (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - Buttons, Reelect R. David Hall (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - Buttons, Clarence Martin for Council At-Large (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - Buttons, Carol Schwartz for Mayor (Box 6, Folder 19)
  - Buttons, Blacks in Government (Box 6, Folder 20)
  - Buttons, "I Voted Washington, D.C. '78", 1978 (Box 6, Folder 21)
  - Buttons, MICCO Citizen Planner (Box 6, Folder 22)
  - Buttons, D.C. Statehood Initiative 3 (Box 6, Folder 23)
  - Buttons, Inner City Aids Network (Box 6, Folder 24)
  - Buttons, Elect Dave Clark (Box 6, Folder 25)
  - Buttons, "Advisory Councils Yes!" (Box 6, Folder 26)
  - Buttons, "I'll Make It Right On" (Box 6, Folder 27)
  - Buttons, "10 Years Changing It Around" (Box 6, Folder 28)
- Series 7: Local and Federal Government, 3 Boxes
  This series includes D.C. Government resolutions in recognition of Margaret Cooper, posters, and certificates of appreciation.
  - Metropolitan Police Department, 1992-1998 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Certificates, Awards, and Recognition, 1973-1998 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Events and Programs, Awards Ceremonies for Environmental Improvement, 1984-1987 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Department of Housing and Community Development Housing Programs, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Model Cities/War on Rats, 1971-1977 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Advisory Neighborhood Commission; Certificates, Awards, and Recognition, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Advisory Neighborhood Commission, Elections Materials, 1976-1987 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Advisory Neighborhood Commission, Laws and Regulations (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Advisory Neighborhood Commission, Correspondence, 1978-1989 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - U.S. Department of the Interior, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Advisory Neighborhood Commission, 12 Years of Outstanding Service Plaque, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Certificates, Awards, and Recognition; Certificates of Appreciation, 1981-1987 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Advisory Neighborhood Commission, Certificate of Election, 1986 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Metropolitan D.C. Police, Crime Solvers Posters (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - D.C. Department of Public Works, Posters (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Office of the Mayor Proclamation, Shaw Day, 1991-10-05 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Shawfest '90 Day Declaration Resolution of 1990 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Margaret Cooper Recognition Resolution of 1989 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Margaret B. "Mother" Cooper Recognition Resolution of 1996 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Margaret Cooper Recognition Resolution of 1983 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - United to Serve America Diamond Award, 1992 (Box 5, Folder 10)
- Series 8: Books, 1 Boxes
  This series consists of the book Marjorie Webster Junior College, Forty-Fifth Year, Session 1964-1965
  - Marjorie Webster Junior College, 1965 (Box 4, Folder 9)